<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Collections | TechSwamp]]></title>
  <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/blog/categories/collections/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-21T11:51:44+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://shr1k.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shrikant]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Collection of Great Podcasts - Part 4 of 4: Science &amp; Technology]]></title>
    <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-4-of-4-science-and-technology/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-03T21:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-4-of-4-science-and-technology</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="/post/2013/05/09/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-1-of-4-news-analysis/">Part 1: News &amp; Analysis</a></li>
<li><a href="/post/2013/05/14/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-2-of-4-quizzes/">Part 2: Quizzes</a></li>
<li><a href="/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-3-of-4-entertainment/">Part 3: Entertainment</a></li>
<li><strong>Part 4: Science &amp; Technology</strong></li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/jot/">Let's Talk About Tech</a></strong></h4>

<p>This show is part of the Saturday Edition news show on BBC Radio 5 Live, hosted by the deep, rich tones of Chris Warburton. It used to be called The Joy of Tech (which explains the URL stub), and features a family of web, tech, and other science-y experts discussing the latest news and updates in their worlds. And most of the time, these experts include Helen Zaltzman and Olly Mann (of Answer Me This! podcast fame) who are just a pleasure and a joy to listen to. Apart from the generallly informative nature of the show, the chemistry that Chris Warburton shares with the guests is simply fantastic.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/timc/">The Infinite Monkey Cage</a></strong></h4>

<p>A witty, irreverent look at the world through the lenses of science with Robin Ince and everybody's favourite scientist who's not Neil deGrasse Tyson, Brian Cox. They only do about 6 shows in a series, and there are two series in a year. This hardly seems enough for this informative and funny show, but that appears to be par for the course for most good episodic British TV and radio programmes.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.radiolab.org/">Radiolab</a></strong></h4>

<p>Hosted by Jad Abumrad and Robert Krulwich, I find it extremely difficult to concisely explain what the show is about. Wikipedia says <em>"The show attempts to approach broad, difficult topics in an accessible and light-hearted manner and with a distinctive audio production style"</em>, but while accurate, somehow this just doesn't capture the true depth of the show. I was skeptical about it for a long time, until I gave it a proper listen. I wasn't instantly hooked, but once you grok what's going on, it's like a light switches itself on and you're suddenly plunged into examining the nature of beliefs ands truths you held to be incontrovertible.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>See all the posts about the podcast collection <a href="/blog/categories/podcast/">here</a></em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Collection of Great Podcasts - Part 3 of 4: Entertainment]]></title>
    <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-3-of-4-entertainment/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-03T21:04:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-3-of-4-entertainment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="/post/2013/05/09/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-1-of-4-news-analysis/">Part 1: News &amp; Analysis</a></li>
<li><a href="/post/2013/05/14/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-2-of-4-quizzes/">Part 2: Quizzes</a></li>
<li><strong>Part 3: Entertainment</strong></li>
<li><a href="/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-4-of-4-science-and-technology/">Part 4: Science &amp; Technology</a></li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/7daysunday">7 Day Sunday</a></strong></h4>

<p>One of a clutch of weekly news satires that I listen to, this is a hilarious panel discussion style podcast hosted by Al Murray. He's joined by Andy Zaltzman most of the time, as well, which just jacks up the funny in the show to new levels. Mostly because of Andy's "boy who cried wolf" relationship with facts. I'm also a big fan of news satire shows and try to watch or listen to most of them.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.answermethispodcast.com/">Answer Me This!</a></strong></h4>

<p>This show has no real reason to exist. Its premise is that listeners send in questions and the daffy duo of Helen Zaltzman (yep, Andy Zaltzman's sister) and Olly Mann -- ably supported by Martin the Sound Man -- answer these questions. Why would these questioners not use the Internet? Because the hosts are just that good, that's why. They aren't really media professionals (or at least, they weren't till this show became famous), which gives the show an endearing quality that is really rather hard to define. I got obsessed at some point and listened to all the free back-episodes that I could, then went out and bought their book, watched all their videos on Youtube and memorised all the jingles. One could never get too much Helen and Olly.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/fricomedy">Friday Night Comedy - The Now Show</a></strong></h4>

<p>This is another satirical take on the week's UK news headed up by Hugh Dennis and Steve Punt. Largely in sketch form, there are also topical funny songs and stand-up routines by popular comedians. This is part of the same Friday Night Comedy podcast as The News Quiz -- the two shows appear to alternate every other month.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.wantsaword.com/">Ian Collins Wants A Word</a></strong></h4>

<p>After listing everything out here, I realised this is the <em>only</em> "shoot the shit"-type podcast that I listen to. That is all Ian Collins and Sideshow Kev do in this show. Not much news, although some big ticket items are occasionaly discussed, with Collins bringing in a pragmatist Tory angle. There are a couple of other sections that are really funny, and my personal favourite is the collection of Random Acts of Irrational Annoyance. They bring on a guest (nearly) every show, and have a bit of light-hearted chin wag. On occasion, they've even brought on people who they were clearly poking fun at (Tony Topping, Alex Jones, and David Icke)!</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/kermode">Mark Kermode &amp; Simon Mayo's Film Reviews</a></strong></h4>

<p>This is <em>the</em> definitive film review show. Mark Kermode is the (<em>very</em> opinionated, and sometimes just <em>wrong</em>!) film critic, while Simon Mayo brings to bear his considerable radio experience and plays a very capable second fiddle. They discuss the top 10 movies at the UK box office for the week, Mark reviews the movies that're released that week, and bring on a prominent film personality to discuss an upcoming project, all intermingled with listener interactions and reviews. All this sounds quite pretty basic, but they do a damn good job of it, and the show has built up a strongly dedicated fan following (yours truly included) over the many years it's been running. Mark Kermode's occasional headlong dive into an outright rant about shitty or annoying movies are quite legendary, with the review of Sex And The City 2 being of the best examples.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/newsjack">Newsjack</a></strong></h4>

<p>This used to be a hilarious sketch show satirising the week's news events, headed up by Margaret Cabourn-Smith. Unfortunately, it's been off air for so long I can barely remember what it was like! I recall it being very similar to The Now Show (mentioned above as part of Friday Night Comedy), so it's possible that it was just subsumed into that programme instead. Which appears even more likely as Cabourn-Smith is a regular fixture over there as well.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/confess">Simon Mayo's Confessions</a></strong></h4>

<p>Every weekday Simon Mayo hosts the drivetime programme BBC Radio 2, which is made up various little bits between song requests, like book reviews, cookery and general talk. One of these bits is the Confessions corner, where listeners write in confessing to some embarassing act in their past that they've not really owned up to. Simon Mayo reads these out, and the assembled panel take a call on whether they'll forgive the sinner or not. The confessions are often quite mundane, but Simon's delivery and the forgiveness banter make this one of the shows I most look forward to every week.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://thebuglepodcast.com/">The Bugle</a></strong></h4>

<p>This is the funniest, and one of the best, podcasts I listen to. Another weekly news satire show (billed as an "Audio Newspaper for a Visual World"), this pdocast features Andy Zaltzman and John Oliver holding forth their hilarious -- and occasionally sensible -- views on the news of the week. This is one of the few shows I've encountered that has a relatively global approach to the news discussed, and also has a fan-base of total nutters. It used to be hosted by The Times Online, then went independent in January 2012. This was shortly after Andy Zaltzman launched a series of hilariously blistering attacks on Rupert Murdoch and the New Corp empire in the aftermath of the phone hacking scandal. Coincidence? Nobody knows.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>See all the posts about the podcast collection <a href="/blog/categories/podcast/">here</a></em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Collection of Great Podcasts - Part 2 of 4: Quizzes]]></title>
    <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/05/14/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-2-of-4-quizzes/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-14T14:21:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/05/14/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-2-of-4-quizzes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="/post/2013/05/09/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-1-of-4-news-analysis/">Part 1: News &amp; Analysis</a></li>
<li><strong>Part 2: Quizzes</strong></li>
<li><a href="/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-3-of-4-entertainment/">Part 3: Entertainment</a></li>
<li><a href="/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-4-of-4-science-and-technology/">Part 4: Science &amp; Technology</a></li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.comedy.co.uk/podcasts/dotherightthing/">Do The Right Thing</a></strong></h4>

<p>A discussion-style show which asks an assembled panel of comedians about the right or wrong thing to do in any given situation. Hosted by Danielle Ward, this show is a reasonable amount of fun but can get really loud and raucous at times. Susan Calman comes on every so often, which is an obvious shot in the arm for any show.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/fricomedy">Friday Night Comedy - The News Quiz</a></strong></h4>

<p>This show is hosted by Sandi Toksvig and is the BBC Radio 4's version of Have I Got News For You - a quiz show based on a satirical take on the news of the week. The News Quiz is pretty much entirely UK-centric. When this show is on a break, then the Friday Night Comedy becomes a topical sketch show called The Now Show hosted by Hugh Dennis and Steve Punt, which is quite funny as well.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.maximumfun.org/shows/international-waters">International Waters</a></strong></h4>

<p>Internation Waters is an interesting concept -- pit a team of two comedians each from the US and the UK in a battle of pop culture trivia. It's also a little different from the other shows in that it appears to be a monthly podcast. That makes me somewhat glad -- I don't think I could take too heavy a dose of the host Jesse Thorn's brand of humour, which is reasonably drowned out here by the 4 comedian guests. (As an aside, his other podcast -- Comedy Bang Bang -- is highly rated in the community, but I've always found it quite dull. Probably because the guests and recurring "funny" bits are not particularly entertaining.)</p>

<p>*[EDIT: I'm mistaken here. The host of Comedy Bang Bang is Scott Aukerman, and not Jesse Thorn. They sound quite the same though.]</p>

<p>A quick note here: All podcasts from MamimumFun.org appear to have a fair amount of monetisation effort behind them in the form of solicitation ads in the middle of the podcasts. I listen to enough BBC/NPR podcasts that this gets a little annoying after a while. YMMV.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.npr.org/programs/wait-wait-dont-tell-me/">NPR's Wait Wait...Don't Tell Me!</a></strong></h4>

<p>Another gem from the NPR stable, "Wait Wait..." is a both a panel as well as a dial-in quiz show. Hosted by Peter Sagal, the prize for victorious callers is a <em>great</em> one -- they get the dulcet tones of Carl Kasell to record a voicemail greeting message for them! Peter Sagal is really extremely funny, and Carl Kasell... well, I would listen to Carl Kasell reading a dictionary out aloud. The panel features some comedians quite regularly, who are also really funny and well-informed. Some large global news items are covered, but this podcast is a whole lot funnier if you're roughly in the know about the US political scene.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.npr.org/programs/ask-me-another/">NPR's Ask Me Another</a></strong></h4>

<p>This is the best "quiz show" podcast I've ever heard so far, and also the best NPR podcast. Shot live in an NY theatre, it throws brainteasers, traditional trivia questions and vocabulary puzzles at a series of contestants. The host is Ophira Eisenberg, who is accompanied by a clutch of "puzzle gurus" and a musician, who is usually <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9gW6yQZyx5w">Jonathan Coulton</a>. Even though it is ostensibly a competition, the good-natured banter that runs throughout is one of the best parts of the show. Fortunately, most of the content here is general pop culture trivia, although heaving a healthy appreciation of US cultural references will significantly enhance your enjoyment.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>See all the posts about the podcast collection <a href="/blog/categories/podcast/">here</a></em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Collection of Great Podcasts - Part 1 of 4: News & Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/05/09/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-1-of-4-news-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-09T14:02:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/05/09/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-1-of-4-news-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love listening to podcasts.</p>

<p>They're a great way to consume informative, thought-provoking and funny content while also keeping abreast of what's happening in the world. Additionally, podcasts are great company for a run or while at the gym, because they engage the mind just enough to keep you plugging away at a constant pace while being distracted away from any tedium and exertion.</p>

<p>In line with my general OCD for keeping my digital assets organised, I've classified my podcast subscriptions into categories in <a href="http://www.beyondpod.com/Android/">BeyondPod</a>. (As a quick aside, BeyondPod is simply the best podcast manager app I've ever used, and is a very functional RSS/Atom feedreader as well!) These categories (and therefore the sequence of posts on this topic) are:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Part 1: News &amp; Analysis</strong></li>
<li><a href="/post/2013/05/14/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-2-of-4-quizzes/">Part 2: Quizzes</a></li>
<li><a href="/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-3-of-4-entertainment/">Part 3: Entertainment</a></li>
<li><a href="/post/2013/06/03/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-4-of-4-science-and-technology/">Part 4: Science &amp; Technology</a></li>
</ul>


<p>As always, a subscription may not fit neatly into just one category, but it'll have to do.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/analysis">Analysis</a></strong></h4>

<p>A great show where a different person  in each episode examines one issue relating to policy or interesting new ideas from multiple angles, in each episode. I may not agree with quite a few parts of some of the discussions, but they're very well researched and presented. A heavy focus on the UK, but some episodes are quite general.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/bbcaq">Any Questions and Any Answers</a></strong></h4>

<p><em>Any Questions</em> is a panel discussion programme featuring a few UK politicians and some people from other walks of life responding to questions raised by members of a live audience, chaired by an absolutely terrific moderator called <a href="https://twitter.com/dimbleby_jd">Jonathan Dimbleby</a>. The politicians are just as useless as you would expect them to be, and tend to waffle on without really answering the questions. After a few months, there is a rather monotonous drone of a buzz-saw going back and forth through popular dead horses. Despite all of this, it still makes for compelling listening. Recommended only if you want to keep a finger on the pulse of rumblings within the UK.</p>

<p><em>Any Answers</em> is a sister programme hosted by <a href="https://twitter.com/tweeter_anita">Anita Anand</a>, where BBC Radio 4 listeners dial in with their take on the issues that were discussed in the prior installment of Any Questions. The latter show is somewhat pointless as a podcast, but some of the viewpoints expressed are quite repulsively fascinating. Also, I greatly admire Anita Anand's handling of Joe Q. Public's heated ramblings. And she's married to <a href="http://simonsingh.net/simon-singh/colourful-biog/">Simon Singh</a>, who is awesome.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/freakonomicsradio">Freakonomics Radio</a></strong></h4>

<p>SuperFreakonomics might have <a href="http://shrik.theswamp.in/2009/10/such-is-life.html">come in for some criticism</a>, but there's no doubt its predecessor Freakonomics kick-started the trend of economists holding forth on interesting linkages between seemingly unrelated phenomena. A little unfairly, I might add, since The Undercover Economist was published a little earlier. The latter could be considered the hipster Freakonomics.</p>

<p>At any rate, the podcast continues the trend of analysing and exploring "the hidden side of everything", and, as the NPR blurb puts it -- "prepare to be enlightened, engaged, perhaps enraged and definitely surprised."</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://feeds.kcrw.com/kcrw/lr">KCRW's Left, Right &amp; Center</a></strong></h4>

<p>This is the first non-NPR American podcast I've regularly listened to. It's a great little 30 minutes of debate between panellists from across the political spectrum (suitably calibrated to an American scale), and the discussions are always impassioned, without devolving into shouting matches. And despite the "present different sides of the issue" approach, the viewpoints are actually quite sensible and interesting.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.npr.org/series/129577422/weekends-on-all-things-considered">NPR Series Weekends on All Things Considered</a></strong></h4>

<p>NPR gets about as close to BBC Radio as an American economic/political system will allow. All Things Considered is a popular news-magazine style of radio show, and the podcast is a curated selection of the stories covered by ATC that week. Great for US-centric news, some general information, and a generous sprinkling of esoteric music, literature and culture.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>See all the posts about the podcast collection <a href="/blog/categories/podcast/">here</a></em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Collection of JS Visualisation Libraries]]></title>
    <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/04/18/a-collection-of-js-visualisation-libraries/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-18T11:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/04/18/a-collection-of-js-visualisation-libraries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick post to make a collective note of some of the few graphing libraries I am attempting to try out over the coming weeks. Base frameworks like D3.js and Raphael.js appear great, but might just be involve too much work if all I want to do is throw together a quick few visualisations.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://nickqizhu.github.io/dc.js/">dc.js</a></strong>: A multi-dimensional charting library built to work natively with crossfilter and rendered using D3.js.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/novus/nvd3/">NVD3</a></strong>: Re-usable charts and chart components for D3.js.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/polychart/polychart2/">Polychart2.js</a></strong>: Graphing library that takes many ideas from the Grammar of Graphics and the R library ggplot2, and adds interactive elements for usage on the Web.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.highcharts.com/download/">Highcharts</a></strong>: Interactive charting library supporting many, MANY types of visualisation!</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/nnnick/Chart.js/">Chart.js</a></strong>: Simple HTML5 Charts using the canvas element. Currently doesn't support interactivity, but looks great.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.flotcharts.org/">Flot</a></strong>: Plotting library for jQuery, with a focus on simple usage, attractive looks and interactive features.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://code.shutterstock.com/rickshaw/">Rickshaw</a></strong>: JS toolkit for creating interactive time series graphs.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://yuilibrary.com/yui/docs/charts/">YUI Charts</a></strong>: A charting module based on the YUI library.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://tenxer.github.io/xcharts/">xCharts</a></strong>: Yet another D3.js based library. Some of the examples don't appear to work currently.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/HumbleSoftware/Flotr2">Flotr2</a></strong>: A fork of Flotr which removes the dependency on Prototype and a few enhancements.</p>

<p>Now it may turn out that most of these end up going unused, but hopefully that means I would have found the best fit library and will stick with it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
