<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Collections | TechSwamp]]></title>
  <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/blog/categories/collections/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-09T16:17:01+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://shr1k.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shrikant]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Collection of Great Podcasts - Part 1 of 4: News & Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/05/09/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-1-of-4-news-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-09T14:02:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/05/09/a-collection-of-great-podcasts-part-1-of-4-news-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love listening to podcasts.</p>

<p>They're a great way to consume informative, thought-provoking and funny content while also keeping abreast of what's happening in the world. Additionally, podcasts are great company for a run or while at the gym, because they engage the mind just enough to keep you plugging away at a constant pace while being distracted away from any tedium and exertion.</p>

<p>In line with my general OCD for keeping my digital assets organised, I've classified my podcast subscriptions into categories in <a href="http://www.beyondpod.com/Android/">BeyondPod</a>. (As a quick aside, BeyondPod is simply the best podcast manager app I've ever used, and is a very functional RSS/Atom feedreader as well!) These categories (and therefore the sequence of posts on this topic) are:</p>

<ul>
<li>News &amp; Analysis</li>
<li>Quizzes</li>
<li>Entertainment</li>
<li>Science &amp; Technology</li>
</ul>


<p>As always, a subscription may not fit neatly into just one category, but it'll have to do.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/analysis">Analysis</a></strong></h4>

<p>A great show where a different person  in each episode examines one issue relating to policy or interesting new ideas from multiple angles, in each episode. I may not agree with quite a few parts of some of the discussions, but they're very well researched and presented. A heavy focus on the UK, but some episodes are quite general.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/bbcaq">Any Questions and Any Answers</a></strong></h4>

<p><em>Any Questions</em> is a panel discussion programme featuring a few UK politicians and some people from other walks of life responding to questions raised by members of a live audience, chaired by an absolutely terrific moderator called <a href="https://twitter.com/dimbleby_jd">Jonathan Dimbleby</a>. The politicians are just as useless as you would expect them to be, and tend to waffle on without really answering the questions. After a few months, there is a rather monotonous drone of a buzz-saw going back and forth through popular dead horses. Despite all of this, it still makes for compelling listening. Recommended only if you want to keep a finger on the pulse of rumblings within the UK.</p>

<p><em>Any Answers</em> is a sister programme hosted by <a href="https://twitter.com/tweeter_anita">Anita Anand</a>, where BBC Radio 4 listeners dial in with their take on the issues that were discussed in the prior installment of Any Questions. The latter show is somewhat pointless as a podcast, but some of the viewpoints expressed are quite repulsively fascinating. Also, I greatly admire Anita Anand's handling of Joe Q. Public's heated ramblings. And she's married to <a href="http://simonsingh.net/simon-singh/colourful-biog/">Simon Singh</a>, who is awesome.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/freakonomicsradio">Freakonomics Radio</a></strong></h4>

<p>SuperFreakonomics might have <a href="http://shrik.theswamp.in/2009/10/such-is-life.html">come in for some criticism</a>, but there's no doubt its predecessor Freakonomics kick-started the trend of economists holding forth on interesting linkages between seemingly unrelated phenomena. A little unfairly, I might add, since The Undercover Economist was published a little earlier. The latter could be considered the hipster Freakonomics.</p>

<p>At any rate, the podcast continues the trend of analysing and exploring "the hidden side of everything", and, as the NPR blurb puts it -- "prepare to be enlightened, engaged, perhaps enraged and definitely surprised."</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://feeds.kcrw.com/kcrw/lr">KCRW's Left, Right &amp; Center</a></strong></h4>

<p>This is the first non-NPR American podcast I've regularly listened to. It's a great little 30 minutes of debate between panellists from across the political spectrum (suitably calibrated to an American scale), and the discussions are always impassioned, without devolving into shouting matches. And despite the "present different sides of the issue" approach, the viewpoints are actually quite sensible and interesting.</p>

<hr />

<h4><strong><a href="http://www.npr.org/series/129577422/weekends-on-all-things-considered">NPR Series Weekends on All Things Considered</a></strong></h4>

<p>NPR gets about as close to BBC Radio as an American economic/political system will allow. All Things Considered is a popular news-magazine style of radio show, and the podcast is a curated selection of the stories covered by ATC that week. Great for US-centric news, some general information, and a generous sprinkling of esoteric music, literature and culture.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>See all the posts about the podcast collection <a href="/blog/categories/podcast/">here</a></em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Collection of JS Visualisation Libraries]]></title>
    <link href="http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/04/18/a-collection-of-js-visualisation-libraries/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-18T11:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://shr1k.github.com/post/2013/04/18/a-collection-of-js-visualisation-libraries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick post to make a collective note of some of the few graphing libraries I am attempting to try out over the coming weeks. Base frameworks like D3.js and Raphael.js appear great, but might just be involve too much work if all I want to do is throw together a quick few visualisations.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://nickqizhu.github.io/dc.js/">dc.js</a></strong>: A multi-dimensional charting library built to work natively with crossfilter and rendered using D3.js.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/novus/nvd3/">NVD3</a></strong>: Re-usable charts and chart components for D3.js.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/polychart/polychart2/">Polychart2.js</a></strong>: Graphing library that takes many ideas from the Grammar of Graphics and the R library ggplot2, and adds interactive elements for usage on the Web.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.highcharts.com/download/">Highcharts</a></strong>: Interactive charting library supporting many, MANY types of visualisation!</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/nnnick/Chart.js/">Chart.js</a></strong>: Simple HTML5 Charts using the canvas element. Currently doesn't support interactivity, but looks great.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.flotcharts.org/">Flot</a></strong>: Plotting library for jQuery, with a focus on simple usage, attractive looks and interactive features.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://code.shutterstock.com/rickshaw/">Rickshaw</a></strong>: JS toolkit for creating interactive time series graphs.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://yuilibrary.com/yui/docs/charts/">YUI Charts</a></strong>: A charting module based on the YUI library.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://tenxer.github.io/xcharts/">xCharts</a></strong>: Yet another D3.js based library. Some of the examples don't appear to work currently.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/HumbleSoftware/Flotr2">Flotr2</a></strong>: A fork of Flotr which removes the dependency on Prototype and a few enhancements.</p>

<p>Now it may turn out that most of these end up going unused, but hopefully that means I would have found the best fit library and will stick with it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
